地         球         脉         动   I I
地球上四分之一的土地
One quarter of all the land on Earth
覆盖着唯一一种伟大的植被
is covered by a single, remarkable type of plant.
它们几乎坚不可摧  一天可以长高六十厘米
Almost indestructible, it can grow two feet in a day...
连巨型动物都能藏匿其中
And be tall enough to hide a giant.
那就是草本
That plant is grass,
草本植物构建出来的世界独具一格
and the world it creates is truly unique.
印度北部的草是地球上长得最高的
The grass in northern India is the tallest on the planet,
这里是众多神奇生物的家园
home to some of the most impressive creatures to tread the Earth.
现在正当好时候
These are the good times,
可再过几个月  这些青草就会消失
but in just a few months, all this fresh growth will be gone,
动物们将被迫迁徙
and the animals will be forced to move on.
地球上的草原都是如此
That is the way things are on grasslands across the planet.
重复着富足  消亡  重生的循环
A cycle of abundance, destruction and rebirth
从而影响着栖息在这里的所有生命
that affects every creature that lives here.
草        原
辽阔的欧亚草原区是地球上最大的草原地带
The largest grassland on Earth, the vast Eurasian Steppe,
覆盖距离达到地球周长的三分之一
stretches one third of the way around our planet.
画 外 音
大卫 · 爱登堡   爵士
青草随春雨而生  也带来了新生命
Spring rain has brought fresh grass, and with it, new life.
一种冰川时代存活至今的生物  高鼻羚羊幼崽
A relic from the Ice Age, a baby Saiga antelope,
出生才三小时
just three hours old.
陪伴它的只有它的孪生兄弟
His only company, his twin.
在它们能站起来之前
Until they can stand,
母亲会将它们藏在草丛中
their mother has left them hidden in the grass.
这样应该很安全  只要保持安静
They should be safe, as long as they remain quiet.
对这两只小羊来说  时间紧迫
For these calves, the clock is already ticking.
羚羊群很快就要离开
Their herd will soon be moving on,
去寻找最新鲜的草场
seeking the freshest new grass.
高鼻羚羊四肢瘦长
Their lanky legs are a sure sign
预示着它们一生都将奔波在路上
that they're built for a life on the move.
高鼻羚羊总会产下孪生幼崽
Saiga always give birth to twins,
这样能够在草源充足时迅速繁衍
so their numbers grow rapidly just when grass is plentiful.
它们的鼻子长相奇怪  却能够勘测到
Their bizarrely shaped nose can detect fresh growth
几百公里外的青草长势
from hundreds of miles away.
这两只小羊即将与其他草原动物一样
The young twins will now begin the nomadic life
开始辽阔草原上不断迁徙的生活
they share with most animals on the world's open plains.
降雨量不足以养育森林时就会出现草原
Grasslands occur where rain is too sporadic for forests to exist.
草原生长所需的年降雨量
The rain that a grassland needs to survive for a year
可能会一次来临
might arrive all at once.
这样的暴雨在二十四小时内能达到三百毫米降雨量
Storms like these can release 12 inches of rain in 24 hours.
淋起来可不好受
Not much fun if you're out in it.
最终土壤无法继续吸收雨水
Eventually the earth can't soak up any more,
草原也完全变了样子
and the grassland undergoes a radical change.
许多植物会被淹死  而草本却会茁壮生长
Many plants would drown here, but grasses thrive.
它们长得飞快
They grow so fast,
茎叶迅速伸出水面  沐浴在阳光下
their leaves quickly rise above the water and into the sunlight.
在南非
Here in southern Africa,
降水能让世界上最奇特的草原之一改头换面
water transforms one of the most remarkable grasslands on Earth,
奥卡万戈三角洲
the Okavango.
每年都有近一万三千平方公里的草原被水淹没
Every year, 5,000 square miles of grassland are flooded.
对于狮群来说  这成了最大的问题
For one pride of lions, this poses a major problem.
虽然猎物众多
There may be plenty of prey around,
但狮子并不擅长在水中捕猎
but lions struggle to run it down in water.
狮群中有三个月的幼崽
The pride has three-month-old cubs.
它们以前从未见过水
They've never seen water before.
如果母狮们短时间内捕不到猎物
If their mothers don't make a kill soon,
这些幼崽可能撑不过这周
the cubs might not survive the week.
受洪水滋养
But fuelled by the flood,
蓬勃生长的青草吸引来新的猎物
the eruption of grass attracts new possible prey.
数量超过两千头的水牛群接踵而至
Buffalo arrive in herds 2,000 strong.
强大  好斗  抱团前进
Powerful, aggressive and united,
狮子能遇到的动物中  水牛是最危险的
they're the most dangerous animal a lion can face.
体型最大的公牛不会逃跑
The biggest bulls don't run.
他们仗着身形庞大  并不惧怕狮子
They're simply too huge to be scared of lions.
重达九百公斤  他比五头母狮加起来都重
At 900 kilos, he weighs more than all five lionesses combined.
虽然狮群占据了数量优势
The pride do have numbers on their side,
但如果被水牛角扫到  可能会直接丧命
but one sweep of his horns could be deadly.
一头母狮正面诱敌
One distracts the bull up front,
她的姐妹从后方进攻
while her sisters attack from behind.
母狮们必须想办法压倒公牛
The cats must somehow topple the buffalo,
但沼泽太过湿滑  脚底无法借力
but with swamp under foot, they can't get any traction.
公牛逐渐虚弱
The bull is weakening,
但狮群也露出疲态
but the lions are tiring, too.
现在是体力与毅力的双重考验
It's now a battle of will as much as strength.
要想活下去  公牛必须想办法甩掉母狮
To live, the bull must somehow shake off the lioness.
这头公牛受了伤
The bull is wounded,
但幸亏有五厘米厚的牛皮  他会慢慢痊愈
but thanks to his two-inch-thick hide, he will recover.
而狮群  只能忍饥挨饿了
For the pride, these are hungry times.
但等到水位降低  便会有新生命来临
But, ultimately, once the water recedes, there will be new life,
也就有了新的食物来源
and new food to benefit all.
只要条件适宜  草本植物可以在短短几天内
In the right conditions, grasses have the extraordinary ability
完成从发芽到开花的全过程
to grow from first shoots to flower in a matter of only days.
青草变成一棵棵微型果树
Grasses become the miniature equivalents of fruiting trees.
对于住在其中的生物来说
And for creatures living within the grass,
这样的草丛就像雨林一样高大葱郁
this is a landscape as vast and towering as any rainforest.
非常适合建造小树屋
And excellent place to build a tiny tree house
供巢鼠居住
for a harvest mouse.
夏季的欧洲草原食物充盈
During summer, European meadowlands are full of food,
只看谁能捷足先登
but only for those that can reach it.
爬草比爬树更困难
Climbing grass is harder than climbing trees,
主要是因为草茎不会静止不动
not least because their stems just won't stay still.
她的尾巴可以抓握物体  就像第五只手
Her prehensile tail acts like a fifth limb,
让她如林中穿梭的猴子一般敏捷灵活
so she's as agile as a monkey clambering around in a tree.
和森林中一样
And just as well,
这片草丛中最好的食物
for the best food in this tiny forest
也在植株最顶端
is at the very top of its canopy.
但爬到高处觅食  就会暴露自己
Feeding up here, she's exposed.
一只仓鸮
A barn owl.
动作不算灵巧
Not her finest move...
但也算成功逃命
But it did the trick.
巢鼠鲜少在地面行动
Harvest mice seldom go all the way down to the ground.
这里的世界复杂而危险
It's a tangled and dangerous world down here.
但她能够通过解读头顶的草茎来辨明方向
But she can read the pattern of the stems overhead like a map,
从而找到回家的路
and so find her way home.
时机刚好
And not a minute too soon.
幼崽嗷嗷待哺
There are mouths to feed.
她的宝宝们必须迅速长大
Her babies must fatten up quickly.
他们要趁着夏季食物充盈时
They need to harvest the summer grasses
尽量进食成长
while they're still rich with food.
非洲稀树草原亦是如此
On the African savannah, too,
应季时草地生命丰富多彩
seasonal grasses are filled with life,
但却不会持续太久
but it won't last long.
红喉蜂虎是卓越的空中猎手
Carmine bee-eaters are superb aerial hunters,
十分擅长捕食飞行中的昆虫
experts at catching insects in midair.
但它们无法将猎物赶出草丛
But they have no way of flushing their prey out of the grass.
一旦警觉起来  大多数昆虫会静止不动
Once alarmed, most insects stay put.
红喉蜂虎需要找帮手来捣乱
The bee-eaters need someone to stir things up a bit.
一只灰颈鹭鸨
A kori bustard.
它是世界上体重最大的飞禽
It's the world's heaviest flying bird,
凭它庞大的身躯  应该能轰出一些虫子
so it should be bulky enough to kick up some insects.
成功了
Bingo!
直到有别的蜂虎加入
Until someone else comes along
打乱它的计划
and cramps your style.
没关系  也许等会还有更好的机会
Never mind, perhaps there are bigger opportunities ahead.
鸵鸟怎么样
What about an ostrich?
它们是体重最大的鸟类
The heaviest bird of all.
这次有足够的交通工具了
This time there's more than enough transport to go around.
很快  几乎每只鸵鸟都有了自己的乘客
Soon, almost every ostrich has its own passenger.
不过搭便车的也得意不了多久
But free riders are only tolerated for so long.
蜂虎真正需要的
What the bee-eaters really need
是体型大到根本注意不到它们的动物
is a creature so big it won't even notice them.
非洲公象夷平草地之势
Nothing cuts a swathe through grass
没有动物能与之比肩
like an African bull elephant.
诀窍是尽可能飞在这位“大块头”的近前方
The trick is to fly as close to the front of the giant as possible.
想取得奖赏  必须在刹那间出手
They only have a split second to grab the prize.
越来越多昆虫被赶出来  竞争也愈发激烈
As more insects are stirred up, the competition intensifies.
夏天即将结束  储备食物的竞赛已然打响
With summer drawing to a close, the race to stock up is on.
草很快就会枯萎  屯食良机转瞬即逝
Soon, the grass will wither, and this opportunity will have gone.
到了旱季
As the dry season takes hold,
地面的食物愈发稀缺
food becomes increasingly thin on the ground.
只有在真正身怀绝技的草原捕猎者
Now, only the most specialised predators on the plains
才能维持生活
can make a living.
她虽然形似猎豹  但这只猫并非短跑能手
She may be spotted like a cheetah, but this cat is no sprinter.
相反  修长的四肢给予她独特的猎捕优势
Instead, she has extra-long legs which give her a high vantage point.
不过薮猫最主要的武器  是她雷达般的双耳
But a serval cat's main weapon are enormous radar ears.
能精确定位草丛中猎物的藏身之处
They help her pinpoint prey hiding in the grass.
可是她的猎物十分机警
But the prey she seeks are canny.
非洲沟齿沼鼠
Southern vlei rats.
他们知道持续移动会暴露行踪
They know that any sustained movement can give them away.
于是选择短距离爆冲
So they move in short bursts.
但是最细微的窸窣声也会被薮猫察觉
But even the slightest rustle will give her a clue.
快找到了
Warm.
更接近了
Warmer.
没抓到
Missed.
形势好的时候  她一天能抓十只
In better times, she could catch 10 a day,
但现在啮齿动物数量极少  她只能挨饿了
but now, with so few rodents around, she will have to go hungry.
随着干旱加剧  草原生活更加艰难
As drought intensifies, life gets tougher for all.
定居于此的捕食者只能选择熬过去
Predators with permanent territories must tough it out,
因为大部分猎物都已远去
while most of their prey disappear over the horizon.
为了抵御饥饿
To avoid starvation,
草原动物大多随水草迁徙
many grassland animals follow a nomadic way of life.
超过两百万头牛羚奔走在东非大草原
Over 2,000,000 wildebeests wander the East African savannahs
追逐着雨水
chasing the rains.
不过它们并不孤单
And they are not alone.
展翅飞来这里
Arriving on the wing,
杰氏巧织雀也在寻找鲜嫩的草
Jackson's Widowbirds also seek fresh grass.
然而  它们却不只是为食物而来
Although, it's not just food that they're after.
这只雄鸟想求偶
This male wants a mate.
为此他已长出漂亮的繁殖羽
He's grown elaborate breeding plumage for this moment,
但他需要舞台来展现自我
but he needs a stage on which to show it off.
细心挑选草茎
By carefully selecting grass blades,
每一根修剪到合适的长度
each trimmed to the correct length,
他正在进行非常独特的创作
he's creating something very special.
他需要一块平地
He needs an even surface,
和一个中央摆设
and a centre-piece.
舞台已经布置好了
The stage is set.
他的单身公寓干净整洁  很能吸引雌鸟
His bachelor pad is sufficiently neat and tidy to attract a female.
问题是
The problem is,
她能看到吗
can she see it?
他还有竞争对手
He has competition.
园艺设计可能不足以打动女士们
It might take more than a little gardening to impress the ladies.
跳起来是个好办法
Jumping is the right idea,
但他低估了草的高度
but he's misjudged the height of the grass.
他的对手显得很轻松
His rival makes it look easy.
他得加把劲了
Time to raise his game.
不仅要看谁跳得高
It's not only who jumps the highest,
还要看谁能跳得久
but who can keep doing so the longest.
对手们无法坚持下去  相继退出竞争
Unable to go the distance, his rivals drop out one by one.
他的耐力吸引了爱侣
Stamina has won him admirers,
现在可以展示他的求爱舞台了
now he can show off his courtship arena...
再来一场浪漫的捉迷藏游戏
And engage in a little romantic hide-and-seek.
他终于得偿所愿
Finally, he's done enough.
东非大草原养育着成千上万的食草动物
The East African savannahs support millions of grazers.
每年会吃掉数百万吨草
Each year they devour millions of tons of grass,
然而有一种生物
and yet there's one creature here
对草原造成的影响  远大于其他动物的总和
whose impact is far greater than all these animals combined.
地球上有草的地方  都有它们的踪影
They're found wherever grass grows on the planet,
但它们的辛苦劳作几乎难以察觉
yet their labours go almost entirely unnoticed.
其中最出色的
One of the most remarkable is found here
出现在南美洲草原
on the grasslands of South America.
这些叶片十分坚硬
These blades are so tough
几乎没有大型食草动物能消化得了
that virtually no large grass eaters can stomach them.
然而却被小小的切叶蚁
Yet they're harvested on an industrial scale...
大规模采集
...by tiny grass cutter ants.
可它们根本无法消化叶片
But they themselves can't digest one bit of it.
那到底是为什么呢
So, why bother?
答案在地下
The answer is underground,
可谓别出心裁
and it's very ingenious.
每根叶片都被切成一定长度  放入菌圃
Each blade is cut to length and placed into a garden of fungus.
真菌以腐烂的叶片为食
The rotting grass feeds the fungus,
而真菌又成为蚂蚁的食物
and in turn the fungus feeds the ants.
养活五百万劳动者需要大规模的高效耕作
But feeding 5,000,000 workers requires intensive agriculture.
幸好它们都很勤劳
Luckily, they are an industrious lot.
仅这一个蚁群  每年就能收集五百多公斤草
This colony alone will collect over half a ton of grass every year.
数十亿蚁群遍布全球草原
With billions of ant colonies across the world's grasslands
都在做相同的事
all doing exactly the same thing,
它们消耗的草数量惊人
that's a mind-boggling amount of grass.
据估计  地球上超过三分之一的草
It's estimated that over one third of the grass that grows on Earth
都会被这种昆虫采去
will be harvested by an insect.
在澳大利亚北部
In northern Australia,
白蚁辛勤的劳作体现在雕塑上
termites memorialise their industry in sculpture.
这些令人叹为观止的白蚁丘有三米高
These astonishing mounds are 10 feet tall.
全部建成南北走向
They're always built on a north-south axis,
因此它们的建筑者被称为罗盘白蚁
which is why their builders are called compass termites.
这些粘土造就的城堡
These castles of clay
保护着它们的主人
protect their builders from extremes of heat
不受草原酷暑和季节性洪水的伤害
and seasonal floods experienced on many grasslands.
白蚁与大多数食草动物不同
Termites manage to do what most grass eaters can't,
它们能分解枯草  提取养分
break down dead grass and extract the nutrients.
但也有动物能探进蚁穴将它们吃掉
But they themselves can be food for those that can reach them.
六十厘米长的舌头
A two-foot-long tongue
上面布满极小的钩子
covered in microscopic hooks,
加之比迅猛龙还要长的爪子
followed by claws longer than those of a velociraptor.
这是一只生活在南美平原上的大食蚁兽
A giant anteater on the plains of South America.
它每天可以吞食两万只昆虫
It can devour 20,000 insects a day.
有力的前肢让它们能够轻易地掰开白蚁巢
Powerful forelegs enable it to rip apart a termite hill with ease.
太阳炙烤草原  白蚁面临着新的危险
And as the sun bakes the grass, the termites face new danger.
几分钟内  大火就将草原化为灰烬
In minutes, fire turns grassland to ash.
但是草不会被大火烧尽
But the grasses are not dead.
它们的地下茎完好无损
Their underground stems are unharmed.
数周  数月就这么过去了
Weeks, months may pass,
但是雨季终将来临
but eventually the rains will return
青草又会重新发芽
and the grass will sprout again.
一些草原不仅要忍受火的炙烤  还有冰霜
Some grasslands must endure not only fire, but ice.
冬季来临
As winter approaches,
北美的草原开始霜冻
the prairies of North America begin to freeze.
夏季  美洲野牛四处漫步
In summer, bison roamed freely,
享用着取之不尽的大片青草
almost continuously cropping the abundant green grass.
现在青草不仅枯萎结冰
Now, that grass is not only withered and frozen,
马上还会被大雪掩埋
it's about to be buried.
六千万吨的积雪覆盖在野牛群的领地上
Sixty million tons of snow now blanket this herd's territory.
在厚厚的积雪中行动非常耗费体力
Pushing through deep snow is exhausting work,
美洲野牛越来越饥饿
and the bison are now slowly starving.
仅仅保暖都需要耗费大量的能量
Just keeping warm saps huge amounts of energy.
他们厚重的皮毛可耐受零下三十度的低温
Their thick coats can insulate them down to minus 20 Fahrenheit.
现在是零下四十度
It's now minus 40.
唯一能让他们活下去的食物
The only thing that will keep them alive
被深埋在一米深的积雪之下
is buried beneath three feet of snow.
他们意想不到的邻居也面临着同样的问题
And that's a problem shared with a surprising neighbour.
狐狸在搜寻的食物也被深埋在积雪之下
The food the fox seeks is also deep beneath the snow.
这两种生物能否生存下去
The survival of both creatures
取决于能否挖到地面的食物
depends on getting through to the ground.
对于美洲野牛来说  用蛮力就可以做到
For the bison, it will be a matter of brute strength.
强大的颈部肌肉让他们每天可以铲五吨的雪
Massive neck muscles enable them to shovel five tonnes of snow a day.
他们小巧的邻居则需要更高的准头
Their light-weight neighbour needs more precision.
美洲野牛达到了目的
The bison have reached their goal,
一大口枯草
a mouthful of withered grass.
在美洲野牛挖过的地方狐狸也见缝插针
And where the bison have dug, the fox now spots an opportunity.
每一步都至关重要
Every footstep counts,
但是时机...
but he mustn't break through...
还未到
Yet.
他仔细监听着猎物的一举一动
He listens carefully to pinpoint his target.
它在移动
It's moving.
一只野鼠
A vole.
虽然小  但是比一嘴干草的
Small, but 100 times more nutritious
营养价值高上百倍
than a mouthful of dried grass.
想要在这草原上度过严冬
To get through the winter on these prairies,
有时候脑子比蛮力更加重要
sometimes brain beats brawn.
最终  所有草原上的生物
Ultimately, life on all grasslands
都依赖于季节的更迭
depends on the turn of the seasons.
在树木生存极限八百公里以北的地方
Five hundred miles further north than any tree can survive,
青草春风吹又生
grass returns to life.
雌性北美驯鹿远赴北方
Caribou females have journeyed to the far north
来此产仔
to calve.
超过七万只驯鹿幼崽
Over 70,000 caribou babies
将在几天内出生
will be born in the next few days.
小鹿出生的时候
As the calves appear,
也正是青草发新芽的时候
so too do the leaves of the newly sprouting grass.
幼鹿必须迅速增强体能
And the calves must strengthen quickly.
几天内他们就将跟随自己的父母
Within days they will have to keep up with their parents
踏上无尽的征程
on a never-ending march.
第一天  他们的速度就已经超过人类短跑健将
At one day old, they're already faster than an Olympic sprinter.
他们正在测试自己跋山涉水用的四肢
They're testing the legs that will carry them thousands of miles,
最好现在就知道极限在哪里
better to learn their limitations now.
看起来很好玩  但草原上最艰苦的生活
It may look playful, but there's no harder life on the grasslands
正等着这些他们
than that facing these infants.
母驯鹿现在聚集起来
The caribou mothers now join together,
每只都带着一只同样大小的幼鹿
each with an infant exactly the same age.
她们准备启程
They're setting off on the greatest
进行陆地上最伟大的长途跋涉
overland trek made by any animal.
但是无论草食性动物走到哪里
But wherever grass eaters travel,
都有捕食者等待着他们
predators lie in wait.
就是他们  北极狼
Here they are, Arctic wolves.
他们必须要在
They must seize their chance
驯鹿经过领地时把握住机会
while the caribou pass through their territory.
北极狼跑向鹿群
The wolf runs at the herd,
试图冲散群体中的弱者
trying to flush out the weak or the slow.
一只幼鹿走散了
A calf is separated.
狼全力以赴捕猎的时速将近六十公里
At full tilt, 40 miles an hour,
只比小鹿快一点点
the wolf is just faster.
但是幼鹿的耐力更好
But the calf has stamina.
虽然只有几周大
Only a few weeks old,
这只幼鹿的求生欲望让人叹为观止
and this calf's will to survive is remarkable.
而且必须如此
And it needs to be,
这些幼鹿开始了一场
for these young caribou have now started a journey
终其一生的旅程
that will last a lifetime.
永远追寻着他们所需要的
Forever chasing the seasonal growth of the grass
季节性生长的青草
on which they depend.
和其他草原生物一样  他们依赖着
Like all grassland creatures, they are at the mercy
这变化莫测而又极其慷慨的大草原
of these unpredictable but ultimately bountiful lands.
青草可以在地球上最为极端的环境下生长
Grass can survive some of the harshest conditions on earth,
经受洪水  火灾和冰霜的考验仍然生机盎然
flood, fire and frost, and still flourish.
所以草原为地球上
So it is that grasslands provide a stage
最壮观的野生动物群提供了舞台
for the greatest gatherings of wildlife on planet earth.
下集预告
Next time,
我们向地球上最新的栖息地进发
we venture to the newest habitat on Earth,
我们的城市
our cities.
揭示在这个人造的世界中
To reveal the extraordinary ways
动物们神奇的生存方式
that animals survive in this man-made world.